Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 7 -- Letters to Franklin 1783 January-November Mss.B.F85inventory07
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 3; A.L.S. 4p.; Steinsky, François. Prague
    Account of an armonica made from Franklin's model; account of various inventions by M. Landriani of Milan. Description of a piece of Polish money of the 15th century, found shut up in a rock. Reason given for the natural formation of a hill on the banks of the Elbe. They now possess an excellent translation in German of Franklin's works. Enthusiastic praise for Franklin and for the great Nation he has helped to found.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Robertson, William. College of Edinburgh
    Introducing his son.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Pinelli, ------ de. Honskotte in Flanders
    Renews his offers of service in his capacity of engineer and architect.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Charged with affectionate farewells by the Comtesse de Deux-Ponts, who goes to Tugny to attend the wedding of her son, and thence to Forbach. His regard for Franklin is a sort of hero-worship. The "America" arrived at Brest; her construction much admired.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 9; A.L. 4p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Charge against Lord Shelburne of having used foul play about the instructions for removing the troops from New York; second charge that he put the Spaniards in possession of Florida to give them an opportunity of quarreling with the America; gives his reasons for not believing these accusations; thinks Lord Shelburne would never be relished by Frenchmen or by ambitious English placemen; believes him to be a fair-meaning, bold statesman. [End of letter missing.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Relating to his bankruptcy; his creditors have expressed confidence in him. Expects to be able eventually to satisfy them all.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Remmel, J. Chrétien and Houba, Jean
    Apply for a free passage to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Perier, -----, baron de. Chateau d'Ussan at Pau
    The cargo on his vessel he was forced to sell at New London for paper money; wishes Franklin's assistance to redeem the amount.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 10; A.L.S. 4p.; Deudon, A.C.G. Paris
    Charged by M. Bournons of the Royal Academy of Sciences at Brussels to send Franklin the first part of his "Eléments de Mathématiques"; promises the next two volumes when they appear. Describes how he has improved the armonica; will gladly come to Passy and give him a practical demonstration.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.] August 10; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Windisch-Grätz, comte de
    Inquiring when he could see Franklin at Passy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Nixon, William. Off the Downs
    Begs permission to dedicate to him a few little books, intended to facilitate the acquisition of the Roman language. The letter he received from Franklin when a prisoner at Valognes in Normandy he destroyed as a precautionary measure; is now en route to Portsmouth, Va., and would very much like another letter from him, in order to procure a professorship in one of the American colleges.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Bry, -----. L'Orient
    His share of prize-money due him as doctor on board "La Vengeance"; Commodore Paul Jones. Desires a place as physician to the Americans, who are about to found an institution at l'Orient.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Mr. [Le] Grand Cannon from Connecticut.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Mr. Russell of Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 12; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Nicolson, Sir James. Passy
    Complains of the action of Dr. Franklin's grandson [William Temple Franklin] in taking away a miniature portrait of Lady Nicolson and insists on its prompt return.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Ransier, Jacques Lambert. Fürth
    Repeats his request for Franklin's protection and advice as well as letters of recommendation to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 13; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Brongniart, Alexandre Théodore. Paris
    Desires to know if he may expect Franklin at his house on Wednesday morning; afterwards they must go to the Military School and to the Invalides, relative to the lightning-rods which the Maréchal de Ségur intends erecting on those two buildings; after this inspection, Le Gouverneur des Invalides desires Franklin's presence at dinner. Franklin will see at M. Brongniart's house the model of the projected column to the glory of Louis XVI.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    [Samuel Cooper] Johonnot arrived too late for the last vessel to New England; will try to get him a passage to Philadelphia; poor opinion of his father.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Unable to procure a passage for [Samuel Cooper] Johonnot at a smaller rate; thinks it will prove cheaper in the long run to send him off at once.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Baron, -----. Dunkirk
    Desiring to know about the prize-money due Messrs. Gognet and Cossont, officers on board the "Pallas" under the command of Paul Jones.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Nairne, Edward. London
    Concerning a book he has sent Franklin containing directions for using his patent electrical machine; the experiments in the philosophical part tend to confirm Franklin's theory of electricity, and the similitude of lightning and electricity. Account of an electrical storm in Oxfordshire which killed thirteen sheep, every one of which had the balls of their eyes forced out.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Johonnot, Samuel Cooper. Nantes
    His arrival at Nantes; his passage to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 15; A.L.S. 6p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Acknowledging the medal and Franklin's favor of May 16th. Delay in the printing of his book; acknowledging Franklin's permission to dedicate it to him. His opinion of the biography of Sir John Pringle by Dr. [Andrew] Kippis, his theological friend, who contributed to fix his anxious mind upon "Socinianisme" as being, in his opinion, the most rational and the only good religion. A paper he intends writing for which he desires philosophical anecdotes about Franklin; begs for a description of the two electrical explosions by which Franklin was hit; description of a like experience to himself; 1 received a severe electric shock whilst making experiments in electricity. Was rendered unconscious for ten or fifteen minutes. Highly injurious effects he felt mentally and physically on first regaining consciousness. After twentyfour hours experienced renewed vigor and great improvement in all his mental faculties; felt much better and stronger than before the shock. Thinks the insane might perhaps be restored to their mental faculties by an electric shock administered to them. Would not however advise anyone to try it on himself. Wishes to publish Franklin's invention of a clock with only three wheels, as well as the curiosity of the globe; begs for his reflections on chimneys. Chances of a war with the Turks, and the danger of having the plague; their custom of fumigating all letters from the East; this is now to be abolished; bewails this criminal act. Application made to him by the Princess of Lichtenstein to intercede with Franklin on behalf of lady [Juliana] Penn. No satisfactory news from Mr. [Samuel] Wharton or [Francis] Coffyn; cannot believe the former is a sharper. Newspaper report that the American people are unwilling to contribute anything to support the public credit.
    1 Translation in French of this account, 4p. (In triplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Jebb, John
    Introducing Mr. Baynes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 17; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Hooke Letang, -----, chevalier de. Paris
    Requests an audience to confer on the best means of forming an establishment in Virginia or Pennsylvania.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 19; A.L.S. 3p.; Gravellinies, ----- Dueil de. Epernay
    Sending the sixty bottles of wine ordered; desirous of supplying the Americans with wines.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Deplorable situation of the American merchants in France; due entirely to the peace; Mr. Grubb's failure; gives him the highest character; recommends Mr. Harrison, who was for some time in Mr. Grubb's office.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 19; A.L.S. 3p.; J.A.C. Sieck formerly Postmaster at Goettingen. Berlin
    Asks for a position in the young Republic. Is able to give valuable secret information concerning the American Revolution. Refers to a previous letter to Mr. Adams. Mentions Secretary Bonhome in the Dutch secret service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Davis, Caleb. Boston
    Enclosing certain letters for Mr. St. John.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 20; A.L.S. 1p.; La Combe, -----, chevalier de. Tulle
    Reported concessions granted by Congress to would-be settlers in America; has the honor to be a French officer of good family but no fortune; desires to know what kind of a reception he may expect in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 20; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Rochambeau, vicomte de
    At the request of the author, M. Telles Dacosta, sends Franklin a book about woods.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 20; A.L.S. 2p.; St. Olympe, -----, chevalier de. Paris
    Acknowledging his kindness in signing his marriage contract; his approaching wedding and the numberless matters incidental thereto must excuse his not pressing the contract in person.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan. Paris
    Concerning an old debt due for shipping some articles to Mr. Richard Bache of Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Vicq d' Azyr, Félix
    Deputed by the Royal Society of Medicine to send Franklin tickets for their public meeting on the 26th; the Society hopes Franklin will be present; intends reading a eulogy on the late Dr. [Sir John] Pringle.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Buquet, Cèsar. Paris
    After thirty years, has brought to perfection his invention for grinding corn; his successful experiments in preserving grain and flour; the results of his work can be found in the printed memoir subjoined.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 22; L.S. 3p.; Maroteau, Joseph. Tournay
    Concerning a family at Tournay, whose talents are as unusual as their ill-fortune has been great. Their knowledge of the manufacture of silk and linen, etc.; if an opportunity should offer to employ them in the service of America, begs Franklin to let him know.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Deux-Ponts, Christian, comte de. Tugny
    Begging Franklin to send the enclosed to the Chevalier de la Luzerne, which includes some lines to his American friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 22; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bruet, -----, comte de. Paris
    Acknowledging the copy [of the Constitutions of the United States] sent him by Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Boudinot, Elias. Princeton
    Requested by his nephew (John M[arsden] Pintard) to beg an introduction for the house of Mr. John Searle and Co., in Madeira; extreme attention paid by this firm to American prisoners who were carried to that island.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 23; L. in 3d P. 1p.; The Ambassador of Sardinia
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Gérard de Rayneval, Joseph-Mathias.
    Has received a letter in favor of Mr. [Burrill] Carnes; thinks if Franklin writes directly to the Comte de Vergennes, the safe conduct will be granted him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Gérard de Rayneval, Joseph-Mathias.
    Returning Franklin the first project for the definitive treaty [of peace with Great Britain]. Encloses a copy of a prescription for gravel; hopes it will be of benefit. Mr. [Jonathan] Williams [Jr.]'s affair will come before the Council on the 29th.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Sieck, J.A.C. Berlin
    Refers to his letter of August 19th. By mistake it was sent under address of Mr. Dumas at The Hague. Encloses duplicate of said letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Pierres, Philippe Denis
    Request made in Franklin's name by the Duc de la Rochefoucauld for twelve copies of the "Constitutions." Repeats his wish for an interview.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Churchill, C. Bennet St. West
    Fears that a multiplicity of business has prevented Franklin from answering his last two letters; begs for a little pecuniary assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Ogden, Col Matthias. Paris
    Wishes to know if it will be perfectly agreeable to Franklin to present him to the King on the following day; the Marquis de la Fayette will be present at the ceremony; if it is not inconvenient, begs for a seat in Franklin's carriage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Tournachon, -----. Paris
    Requesting the position of Consul at Genoa for M. Aimé Bonnafons.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 27; L. in 3d P. 1p.; La Rochefoucauld, Louis Alexandre, duc de
    Acknowledging the copies of the American Constitutions sent him by Franklin; much concerned to hear of his indisposition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 27; A.L. 3p.; -----, -----. Brest
    Presents the claim of an American sailor called Springer, now at Brest, against a certain man, Lelay, who had collected 2,496 francs from the French Admiralty for Springer's account. The claim arose from the sale of a sloop seized in the cove of Cork by seven American sailors who were escaped prisoners from an English jail. The sloop was declared a lawful prize by the French Admiralty and ordered sold, the proceeds to be distributed amongst the seven sailors. Lelay who collected Springer's share as attorney for the latter refused to turn over to him the full amount of his share. Asks Franklin to intervene.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Johonnot, Samuel Cooper. Nantes
    Acknowledging his fault and promising to profit by it. Expects to sail with the first fair wind.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Cambray-Digny, Louis-Antoine-Jean-Baptiste, chevalier de. Paris
    His desire to obtain advancement at Court; wishes particularly to interest in the Comte de Vergennes in his behalf; begs Franklin to write the Count a letter; enumerates his services to the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 28; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Calder, John Dr. London
    Reminding Franklin of a letter which was to be sent to the Hotel d'Espagne for Lieut.-Gen. Melville, and which never came to hand; the bearer, Mr. P. Elmsly will carry any letters Franklin may care to send to London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Platen, M.E., douairière de. Gartz in Rugen
    Begging for news of her son, Philip de Platen, who left France seven years before, to enter the service of the United States; since then has heard nothing of him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 30; A.L.S. 4p.; Duplan, Jean-Pierre. Lausanne
    Reminding Franklin of his promise to subscribe to their encyclopaedia of thirty-six volumes; desires his assistance in order to encourage the sale of this work in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Thieriot, Ph. Bordeaux
    About to sail, in the ship "Nancy," for Philadelphia; pleased to be honored with Franklin's commands.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Pierres, Philippe Denis
    Sending Franklin the quarto copy [of the American Constitutions] for the Grand Duke of Russia, and also the one in octavo.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Durey de Meinières, Octavie Guichard. Aux Pavillons du Chaillot
    Asking for a copy of the "Constitutions" translated by M. de la Rochefoucauld; hears it cannot be bought; would be proud to possess a copy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783. August ?]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Fox, George
    Will wait on Franklin on Thursday and receive his commands for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August; A.L.S. 4p.; Aerts-Smith, Thérèse. Brussels
    Mrs. Williams unable, so far, to trace the whereabouts of her husband whose late letter, dated 1778, spoke of sailing for Boston; her miserable situation, deprived of a support, if he is living, and of his effects, if he is dead; encloses a memoir containing all the details [3p.]; begs Franklin's assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Caffiéri, Jean Jacques
    Congratulates him on his recovered health; begs him not to forget his offer, in case Congress desires to erect any monuments to the glory of the Nation or to the Generals who contributed thereto.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 1; A. Verses. 1p.; Thiriot, J
    In praise of Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 1; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Littlepage, Lewis
    Thanking him for acquiescence in his request to be sent to Congress with the definitive treaty; as Mr. Jay has declared himself decidedly in favor of Mr. Adam's clerk, begs Franklin not to trouble to propose him; will inform the Marquis de la Fayette what deference Franklin paid to his recommendation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Desire of Count Chotek, Chancellor of Bohemia and Austria, to have the enclosed list of American plants sent to a good botanist who will at once forward the grains of seeds to Amsterdam. Urges Franklin to finish his glorious career in philosophical tranquility. His hopes of seeing Franklin in Vienna. Contented with what he has acquired by saving the most illustrious Princess of the world from a disease so fatal to her family; he enjoys in philosophical obscurity more real happiness than a conqueror of a world.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Briant, -----. La Chapelle
    Concerning a relative who in three years has lost all his fortune and most of his family; his purpose to start life again in a new country; thought it possible that Franklin might lessen for them the great expense of a trip to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Gouhard, -----. Nantes
    Sends a request addressed to [Jonathan] Williams [Jr.] by John Mehegam, Carmelite at Brest, on behalf of poor Springer who is in a deplorable situation. Change of plans in the sailing of his vessel obliged [Samuel Cooper] Johonnot to apply for a further loan, which he granted him; gives the total of the amount borrowed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 2; L.S. 2p.; Vermonnet, Jean-Baptiste-Arthur. St. Domingo
    Account of his services to America; applies for the position of His Majesty's Vice-Consul for the United States; begs Franklin to intercede with the Minister on his behalf; encloses a memoir, in French, setting forth his services and the reasons for his request [2p.].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 3; L.S. 3p.; Enoch Freeman, Jedediah Preble, Samuel Freeman, Timothy Dike, John Waste Committee of the Sufferers in Falmouth, Casco Bay. Falmouth, Casco Bay
    Transmitting to Franklin's care the enclosed address; hope the unhappy circumstances of their case will justify their application for relief; suggest the appointment of persons at different ports of France to receive any donations which may be offered; this will be handed Franklin by their friend, the Honorable James Bowdoin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Martin, ----- Du Bois. Paris
    M. de Both desires to know if Franklin ever received his letter of February 24th, and begs that the answer may be confided to the writer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Giordana, François. Turin
    Offers his services to the United States for the establishment of a silk manufactory.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Briaud, -----. Caen
    Desiring to go to America and practise his trade of carpenter and joiner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Faudoas, Léonard (?), vicomte de. Paris
    Begging for letters of recommendation on behalf of a merchant-captain in Havre-de-Grace, who is about to sail for Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 4; L.S. 1p.; Nolin, abbé -----. Paris
    Thanking him for the trouble he took about the boxes of seeds which will arrive from America for him; sends a letter which he begs may be forwarded.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 6; L.S. 3p.; Houdetot, Comtesse d'
    Writes on behalf of a poor sailor in the American service, who is unjustly imprisoned; begs Franklin to write a line to the Intendant at Caen in order to procure the poor fellow's release; M. de Crevecoeur wrote to her about him; will gladly provide the necessary funds to carry him to L'Orient. Looks forward with great pleasure to Franklin's little visit to Sanoir.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Du Ponceau, Jean-Michel, chevalier. Sarrelouis
    Since his return with the army of Rochambeau, has received no news of his brother [Peter Stephen Du Ponceau] who is employed at Philadelphia in foreign affairs; fears his letters have miscarried; takes the liberty of sending the enclosed under Franklin's care.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Angiviller, Charles-Claude de Flahault La Billarderie, comte d'. Paris
    Delighted to be able to procure him the privilege of seeing the beauties of the salon with greater convenience; the aim and object of works of art.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Vicq d' Azyr, Félix
    Expressing his own concern as well as that of the Royal Society of Medicine, for Franklin's indisposition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Bridgen, Edward
    Transcribes a copy of the letter of Bridgen and Waller sent to the Honorable R.R. Livingston at Philadelphia concerning their offer to furnish the States of North America with a copper coinage; apologizes for sending the original to Philadelphia, without again consulting the Commissioners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Bache, Richard. Philadelphia
    Received the enclosed packet from Cape François; the other packet for Comte de Barbancon, he forwards, by [William] Bartram's request, to Franklin's care. Changes in the weather; prevailing sickness. Death of Mr. Joseph Turner and Mr. [Governor James] Hamilton. Increase of population by foreign immigration.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 8; A.L.S. 4p.; Bauer, Johann Christoph. Goettingen
    Is a glass and brick manufacturer. Refers to an advertisement in the "Dantziger Zeitung," that glass-blowers could profitably locate in America. Detailed account of the establishment of a mirror factory, how it could be accomplished. He would make a venture in Flemish and mirror glass and refund money advanced by means of yearly payments.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Jean de Neufville and Co. Amsterdam
    Begging leave to send a letter to His Excellency John Jay, under Franklin's cover. Changes in the name of their firm.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Bays, ----- de. Nuits